welcome Ecom Logistics Nation thank you
for joining today's episode we're on a
mission to share e-commerce Logistics
insights Trends successes and challenges
from the leaders and innovators in our
space
regardless of the size every brand has
similar challenges and I like to tell
them the most important thing in the
contract is not in the contract so it's
like any long-term marriage or
partnership the ability to get along
work together when problems happen
that's where things go left welcome to
the Ecom Logistics podcast we're here
once again at shop talk excited to be
joined by Scott Weiss vice president
technical sales warehousing and
distribution service at Maersk Scott
thank you for joining us thank you for
having me absolutely as a way getting
started can you share a little bit about
your yourself and your experience in the
supply chain space sure um I've been in
the global supply chain industry since
um 1996. so okay 30 years I'm the vice
president of technical sales for mersk
mersk has approximately 158 warehouses
in North America so I help oversee all
of our Omni Channel and Ecom installment
operations across North America
amazing amazing well thank you for
joining us today and start on a stat I'm
not very proud of having been in the
space for a very long time but the
reality is over 50 percent were the
majority of relationships between Brands
and 3pls and in a divorce and we all
have to work hard to to fix that and to
to right the ship but you love the fact
that you've been into space for so long
certainly with your role leading
technical sales you see a lot you hear a
lot you know you're talking to companies
that are exploring a new 3pl partner so
why do you think that percentage is so
high and any thoughts of advice to to
Brands and retailers on on how to look
for a strategic partner yeah and we deal
with brands of all sizes startups to
Fortune 500 publicly traded companies
and you know regardless of the size
every brand has similar challenges and I
like to tell them the most important
thing in the contract is not in the
contract so it's like any long-term
marriage or partnership the ability to
get along work together when problems
happen that's where things go left
that's one thing and we all we always
know in any partnership especially
warehousing problems happen things
happen that we didn't foresee and then
the management the people involved in
the day-to-day is so key if you have
high turnover and it goes both ways the
customer could have high turnover if you
have poor forecasting and planning maybe
you gave the profile information to the
3pl 3pl didn't ask the right questions
or the data wasn't accurate you're going
to have problems long term so the most
important thing in the contract is not
in the contract and so during that
research and Discovery phase it's very
important to look for any of those red
flags from both sides I think that's an
amazing point and you know we lead the
selection process for for a bunch of
mid-market Brands as they're looking to
find you know a new 3pl partner and what
we're hearing now more than ever is the
price will figure out price is going to
be Market competitive no one's going to
be way overpriced that will make sense
give me operational excellence give me a
strong technology integration make sure
those two boxes are checked and equally
important tell me about your account
management structure you're right we
don't live in a perfect industry there
is no 100 SLA so talk to me about maybe
what you've seen be a successful
relationship from you know how how
escalations take place what what type of
you know is it a call center that works
best you know when issues arise is it
dedicated account management like what
have you seen be really successful well
I always like to tell the customer we're
interviewing you just as much as you're
interviewing us so that's the first step
to make sure as a 3pl that you the
customer are actually a good fit for us
and not every customer is a good fit
whether it's the vertical they're in the
size they're in their profile it could
be wholesale and you only do Ecom or it
could be Ecom and you only do wholesale
so that's the first step so once you've
arrived at the agreement the
Partnerships in place I also like to
tell customers you want your 3pl to do
much more than just fulfill orders you
want them to add value by giving best
practices that's the value of a 3pl
we're handling all these other brands so
what is working for the other brands
what we're doing no need to recreate the
wheel so the grade 3 PLS are going to
add a lot more value and make you better
by bringing those best practices to your
organization that that would be one
thing then the account management is
very key is it just you know one
day-to-day person that you're talking to
or someone like you know um a grade 3pl
can have a lot more structure make you
better have an account manager have
continuous Improvement tracking the soas
and kpis and just make you a better
operation by adding a lot more Dimension
than just getting API orders picking a
unit I always like to say that's the
easy part of the relationship is picking
the the each is it's you gotta add value
and you got to have these open
discussions quarterly business reviews
monthly SLI and kpis annual business
reviews it's a partnership it's a
marriage you're an extension of the
company and so one of the things we do
that is just my favorite part is
whiteboarding sessions with these Brands
where our supply chain design team will
fly into their corporate office
will you know turn the lights off lock
the door for six hours and will flow
their Global supply chain and invariably
there's going to be five or six things
that we see that they're doing today
that they shouldn't be doing or
suggestions we can have to make them
better and that could be millions and
dollars of savings so maybe you know we
were five cents more per order on the
Fulfillment side but we're able to save
them millions of dollars or create brand
loyalty and great customer experience so
that's the difference between a good 3PO
and a great 3PO and you know something
really interesting what you just said
and this is an observation I've had as
well in the market is 3pl sit in a such
a good position to be the supply chain
advisors to mid-market Brands because
you know dealing with the large
organizations that have supply chain
teams or that have dedicated analysts
for like inventory dedicated and
analysts for like just relationship
management Etc versus brown brands that
you deal with even a hundred million 200
300 million gmv brand they don't know
supply chain right like they have put in
Blood Sweat and Tears into making this
business work and 3pls actually sit in a
really good position to provide them
advisory I I think there is not enough
consultative work that is going on
exactly that right like you could
literally save millions of dollars by
just making a slight change like give
them a network analysis or you know be
able to heat map center of gravity
analysis should I be in the middle of
the country should I have two DC's
should I have three Network optimization
models three PLS can offer all of that
and you're right the mid-tier they're
great at marketing and selling products
and they'd probably be the first to tell
you they're not great at Logistics and
they don't need to be that that's why we
exist right right markets here yeah
because most of the analysis and service
that is provided at least what I've seen
in the market is like I'll give you a
great UI tool where you can see your
order
but that supply chain optimization and
how you should be doing I think there is
more opportunities going Beyond in you
know we talk a lot about shipping right
breaking down some of the hypothesis
that they have around shipping as well
right like helping them out three PLS
are seeing all of these other brands
what's working in the market what's not
working in the market in a consultative
way working with these Brands I think
more of this needs to be happening in
the market for sure yeah I like to call
us trusted advisors your in-house
Consultants yeah you know and it comes
back to you know working with Brands is
we don't want account management to be
reactive we want it to be proactive so
yes solve the issues and problems that
that occur because again it's imperfect
but give me that proactive information
give me some nuggets of information that
could help me make some meaningful
changes and you know Scott one of the
things we were talking about that I
think you have an interesting
perspective and again people are going
to probably listen to this podcast and
say Maersk I didn't realize they did
e-commerce fulfillment right I know
about the container shipment I like to
say the great thing is we're a great
steamship line and the bad thing is
we're a great steamship
but I think you know through your
Discovery and conversations you know
with with clientele and Prospects if you
helping them on the complete Journey so
maybe you could talk a little bit about
you know what clients are asking for
with a partner when it comes to helping
me Source my product all the way through
making a delivery to the to the final
customer yeah the client is asking for
that and I would say it's regardless of
the size you would be amazed you know
publicly traded Fortune 500 they need
just as much help as the mid-tier to
Startup it's all relative absolutely but
it really starts you know questions like
where should my DC be well we need to
look at the inbounds from Asia where's
your factories are they in Europe um
what what about your outbounds exactly
let's look at that heat map and see
where your penetration is in the
Northeast are you bigger in the South so
to answer anybody's question as they're
looking at it it you need to look at the
whole picture inbound real estate labor
and outbound before you can give them
the answer and so that Global Supply
Chain looking at that whole piece of the
puzzle is the only way you're going to
give the best possible uh answer and
recommendations by looking out of that
and you know mersk is fortunate because
we do offer services from Factory to
Door asset based so we're unique because
we have those services and we can see
the gauge of you know the transit time
and the cost from China to LA versus
Savannah or the outbound small parcel is
it two days from Columbus and you can
hit the whole country we can look at all
those scenarios and you really do need
to look at the whole picture of the
global supply chain to get the best
possible answers these days do you from
a consultative standpoint would you is
it different departments or as far as
the client is concerned you are
essentially working you know one account
one management to say okay I'm also
going to help you with ocean Freight I'm
also going to help you with Trucking and
I'll also help you with the e-commerce
yeah because I see a lot of that right
like it's like oh for this you got it
five percent manager and you got to talk
to that person right we talked about
that last night yeah yep mersk I think
has really been smart it's a global
integrator strategy I'm from Factory to
door and the way we're set up is there's
one Global account manager for that
customer so they're the main point of
contact and then when we have let's say
a warehouse opportunity I'm the
warehouse technical sales expert that's
brought into the discussion I live and
breathe warehousing I call them
connectors and so they connect with the
trucking with the small parcel maybe
they need a warehouse in Asia we have LF
Logistics that we just acquired so we
have experts for each of the subjects
that the customer needs and it seems to
work really well that makes a lot of
sense yeah maybe one of the things that
I know a lot of brands or retailers is
you know searching for a new provider or
maybe a provider for the first time or
maybe they actually do their own
fulfillment they're trying to understand
what is the right number of nodes I
should have in my network and again I
think that certainly correlates to
knowing your customer and what that and
customer experience requirement is
whether it's a two-day delivery five day
seven day whatever it might be but what
are you seeing on that front you know I
think there was this kind of immediate
expansion of nodes in a network when
Amazon came out with you know two-day
Prime and everyone was trying to match
that and and open up you know three four
five node networks we're seeing at least
I'm seeing to an extent a little bit of
a consolidation in there because there
were some issues so maybe just talk
about maybe the pros and cons of a
single node Network first multi-node
that you've been seeing in the market I
would say the 3pl world that's not a
one-size-fits all model and it really
varies by customers so as an example a
footwear apparel and accessory customer
that has 50 000 active skus very
challenging to manage multiple
inventories a Cosmetic Company that
might have 300 active skus more feasible
and realistic to have multiple skus yeah
so that's one thing your SKU cow is the
first thing to look at
um the next thing I really always look
at is who's paying for the outbound free
so in the Ecom world it's mostly really
prepaid you're paying it's shipping
under your account or our account so
that's a big factor of the cost of the
outbound Transportation because that's
more than the Fulfillment costs a lot
more yeah but what if you have collect
payment with your retail Sellers and
it's Wholesale in your Omni Channel then
it makes sense to look at the closest
Port of Entry like a Savannah or Anala
Southern California so that's you know
some brands are a hundred percent d2c
many are Omni channel that have the
collect and the prepaid and some are
only collect and so that's that's a big
factor and then the third one is let's
assume you have all this prepaid your
outbound freight costs a lot what is
important to you is it the cost or the
transit time some customers commit to
their to their customers two-day Transit
time then the multiple DC's is more in
Play While others say you know I have a
product that people can live with
getting in a week and I want the
low-cost solution then maybe the you
know ones DC models in play what we see
for the multi DC models are East Coast
and West Coast primarily not many have
more than two DC's and then um if it's a
1dc model for D to C the Midwest becomes
very attractive due to lower real estate
costs and hitting the whole Us in two to
three days awesome advice that makes a
lot of sense I know nanad you were
wanting to jump in on all things
Automation and Robotics yeah I
specifically robotics right like what's
the Vantage Point like are the customers
asking for robotics absolutely it should
the customers be asking for robotics
like shouldn't they be asking for the
dollars and cents right and efficiency
is your job but why are the customers
asking for that there's a perception
that there's a labor shortage which
certainly after covet there was yeah um
and there still is for a lot of
Warehouse providers to find labor um the
costs of Labor keeps going up it's not
going to go down did you hear that stat
yesterday came out just on that
particular note was they said Amazon's
going through so much labor attrition
that in two years they will have run out
of Workforce unless they rehire no the
workforce would be done like you
to a point where there is no one left
that wants to come and work for you wow
well I would add on that though let me
add that because employee uh retention
I've seen a big increase for uh
companies that have their own
warehousing three PLS the value of
treating an employee and taking care of
them has never been higher that's one
thing that really came out of covid that
companies frankly did not pay as much
attention to before you know whether
it's barbecues promotions certificates
so I'm really happy to see that but that
being said Robotics and automation is a
very common uh request yeah we have a
whole Global
um Innovation Center we're actually
opening up in Jersey City next month we
have about 24 different initiatives
proof of concepts of Robotics uh Goods
to person wrote fetch robotics fabric
robotics so a lot lots lots of all these
initiatives but the key here is it isn't
needed for everybody you know the key is
what works best for your specific needs
Mr and Mrs customer not a one size but
we have all these you know 24 different
options that we look at and we see what
what is the payback what's the
productivity increases and we present
that to the customer and there's
certainly some customers that don't need
automation yeah but there's many that
that do and it's probably a number one
question we're asked these days from the
customer there is that perception that
workers are the prices are going up
they're not as reliable makes sense and
it's very it is a very real issue but um
a 3pl or Warehouse provider that takes
care and really stresses employees it's
a balance between the two I agree right
well all I wanted to you know bring up
was the fact that customers shouldn't be
dictating that right like it should be
other than like you you got capital
investment in automation right then you
got pain share gain share it starts
making sense the customer says let's
let's go put a five million dollar
automation piece as an example right but
when it comes to robotics right like
it's most of it is robotics as a service
yeah right it's on demand if the 3pl
thinks that's the right thing to do
they'll just do it right but the
customers definitely want the cool
factor and I'm sure from a selling
perspective it helps having robots help
so what we do what I found helpful is we
show them a manual solution
semi-automated solution could be
conveyors and then a fully automated
solution for those that might be in that
category and we show them the
productivity difference the capex
startup difference and um the number of
employees so then we help them make it
together an informed decision we don't
just say this is our solution take it or
leave it we present them with options
absolutely and we find that to work
really well makes all the sense in the
world well I apologize from talking
about sexy robotics to dirty palettes
but Scott we were talking about this uh
earlier today and you're in a lot of
warehouses right you go when you get to
tour a lot of facilities and one of the
things you're seeing more often than not
is inventory that's been sitting for
years and not just one two you're
talking five six seven years and you
know we've got all the the technology we
have all the the reporting and insights
and the cost of automation is really
high the last thing you want to be do is
jamming inventory stale inventory into a
highly automated facility so maybe
people are pulling it out putting it in
reserved locations but off-site
locations but what are you seeing you
know why is that actually even happening
in 2023 and and your thoughts on that
yeah so I've never seen more access
inventory in my entire 25-year plus
career I always tell every customer
you're not alone because it's everybody
you know from the uh the line at the
Port everybody over over ordered and so
the reasons that I've seen I like to
tell customers don't fall in love with
your inventory so that's number one the
sales team likes to fall in love with
the inventory number two is the long
lead time of the global supply chain so
as we have this uh podcast today it's
March and the lead time for most brands
is around six months and so economic
uncertainty was a big theme I heard at
the recent TPM conference what is the
economy going to be like six months from
now who really knows yeah and so that
Global Logistics lead time has created
really big challenges on trying to get
your crystal ball out on what you should
order and then the uh the sales team
just falling in love with the inventory
and say it didn't sell last year but
it's gonna sell this year and the the
third reason is the lack of focus on
what those costs are of carrying the
excess inventory putting a dollar amount
on that owner once told me many years
ago that's cash sitting there on the
warehouse floor right you know I think a
big Miss is Brands just putting a dollar
amount of paying uh storage and taking
up space for five years because believe
me I've seen recently five years six
years seven years inventory sitting
there it's pretty amazing and
mind-blowing but it's true well they're
hoping for some Trend to come back I
would imagine well listen Scott really
really appreciate you joining us today I
want to give you the opportunity to let
everyone know you know how they could
learn more how they could reach out to
you how they can learn more about
e-commerce fulfillment solution I mean
if you go on mersk.com
m-a-e-r-s-k.com we have a whole Ecom
fulfillment division
um like I said a warehouse econ
fulfillment centers all over North
America as well as Canada and Mexico
yeah just great websites got all of our
locations and happy to reach out
directly to me I'm based in Los Angeles
so I'll take you out to lunch anytime
amazing thank you very much thank you
Scott you're welcome thank you for
having me be sure to subscribe to the
podcast to maximize your supply chain
available on all major podcasting
channels thank you for listening and see
you in the next episode
foreign